Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- L
  - Leonard, Pat, Jul 21, 2011; cuid34610 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Pat Leonard (b. Manhattan, New York, 1944), the daughter of immigrants from Co. Kerry, grew up in the Inwood section of Manhattan. She lived in the Bronx and in Boston before settling in New Jersey with her husband and children.
  - Leonard, Peggy, May 19, 2011; cuid34611 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Peggy Leonard (b. West Babylon, New York, 1941), the daughter of immigrants from Arklow, Co. Wicklow, grew up in the Chelsea section of Manhattan. Her father was the long-time proprietor of O'Neill's Bar & Grill (now operating as Moran's) in Chelsea, a popular eating establishment for longshoremen for many decades.
  - Long, George, Mar 27, 2012; cuid34612 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    George Long (b. New York, New York, 1940) is the son of Irish immigrant parents from Arklow, Co. Wicklow, and he grew up in Manhattan's Chelsea neighborhood. He worked on the Chelsea Piers as a longshoreman in his teens, but then moved on to become Vice-President of a prominent New York City bank before his retirement. He retired with his wife, Bonny, to Belle Harbor, New York.
    Joe Long Oral History Collection (AIA 070)
  - Long, Joseph, Apr 21, 2012; cuid34613 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    Joseph Long (b. New York, New York, 1952) is the son of Irish immigrant parents from Arklow, Co. Wicklow and grew up in Manhattan's Chelsea neighborhood. He spent his career in management with United Technologies and Otis Elevator. He has a Master's Degree in Irish and Irish-American Studies from Glucksman Ireland House, New York University.
    Joseph Long Oral History Collection (AIA 070)
  - Long, Veronica (Bunny), Mar 27, 2012; cuid34614 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    Veronica "Bunny" Long (b. Bronx, New York, 1943) is the granddaughter of Irish immigrants from Co. Tyrone. She grew up in the Bronx and married George Long.
  - Loughran, Erin, Jun 29, 2011; cuid34615 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Erin Loughran (b. Englewood, New Jersey, 1988), an All Ireland champion on the fiddle who was the 2011 New York Rose of Tralee, is the daughter of the Irish musicians Margie Mulvihill (a Bronx native) and Frank Loughran from of Co. Tyrone. She earned a B.A. in Irish Music and Dance at the University of Limerick and teaches music throughout New York and New Jersey.
  - Lynch, Danny; Kissane, Pat; Keane, Chris; Brosnan, Sean, Oct 24, 2006; cuid34616 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Lynch, James, Apr 27, 2012; cuid34617 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    Dr. James Lynch (b. Queens, New York, 1965) is the only child of postwar Cavan immigrants. He grew up in Elmhurst, Queens, surrounded by extended family on both his father's and mother's sides. Having attended Catholic schools, he attended medical school and specialized in psychiatry. He watched in horror from his Brooklyn Heights office as the Twin Towers crumbled on 9/11. He is married to an Irish-American and has two children. Dr. Lynch is often consulted in cases related to sexual abuse in Ireland.
  - Lynch, Jimmy, Nov 9, 2006; cuid34618 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Lynch, Thomas, Nov 16, 2010; cuid34619 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Thomas Lynch (b. Detroit, Michigan, 1948) is an author and undertaker. He has published several books of poetry, fiction and non-fiction including Skating with Heather Grace (1987), Grimalkin and Other Poems (1994), The Undertaking: Life Studies from the Dismal Trade (1997) and Apparition and Late Fictions (2010). He has been running his family funeral home in Michigan since 1974.
  - Lyons, Martin, 2014; cuid34805 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_83)
    Martin Lyons was born in 1936 in Cashel, County Galway, Ireland. He immigrated to the United States in 1959. He was a co-founder and first chairman for the state of New York for the American Congress for Irish Freedom and a co-founder and first chairman of the Irish Northern Aid Committee (NORAID).
    This interview was conducted by Miriam Nyhan at Martin Lyons's home in Prattsville, New York on August 21, 2014. The interview covers Lyons's early life in Ireland, his life in the United States (US), and his participation in Irish republican organizations. Lyons discusses his father's and uncle's experiences during the Irish Civil War as members of the Third Western Battalion of the Irish Republican Army (IRA) and his experiences growing up in a family involved in Irish republican politics. He discusses his immigration to the US in 1959, his decision to settle in New York City, and his working life in the city. He discusses his introduction to the IRA in New York City and the organization of the IRA in the US. He discusses his introduction to George Harrison in New York City, the difference between the IRA in the late 1950s and in the 1970s, and the work of Lyons and others to revive the interest in Irish civil rights in the US. He discusses his work with others to establish the American Congress for Irish Freedom and the Irish Northern Aid Committee (NORAID) and his work as the chairman of both organizations. Throughout the interview, he recounts stories of his experiences in these and other Irish American republican organizations, and his experiences with members of these groups from the 1960s through the 1980s. He discusses his identity as Irish and Irish American, and his children's identity as Irish Americans.
  - Lyons, Siobhan, 2015; cuid34806 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_50)
    Siobhan Lyons was born in 1973 in Killowen Grange, County Down, Northern Ireland. Lyons graduated from the University of London with a bachelor's degree in Arabic. She married in 2004 and immigrated to the United States. She moved to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania in 2006 and became the program director for the World Affairs Council of Philadelphia. In 2015 she was the Executive Director at the Irish Immigration Center of Philadelphia.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll on April 16, 2015 in the Irish Immigration Center of Philadelphia in Upper Darby, Pennsylvania. The interview contains Siobhan Lyons's early life and family history. She discusses her family's international moves due to her father's work for the Irish Department of Foreign Affairs. She recalls her interest in Arabic due to her father's posting in Saudi Arabia. She describes her visa application process from 2004 to 2007 and its effects on her job application process in the United States. Lyons describes her work with the senior citizens of Philadelphia as the Executive Director at the Irish Immigration Center of Philadelphia.
- M
  - MacCurtain, Sr. Margaret, Apr 25, 2013; cuid34620 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    Sr. Margaret MacCurtain (b. Cork City, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1929) is a noted Irish historian, teacher, editor and human rights activist. Her impressive body of work includes the book Ariadne's Thread: Writing Women into Irish History.
  - MacGearailt, Micheál, 2015; cuid34807 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_85)
    Micheál MacGearailt was born in 1941 in Dingle, County Kerry, Ireland. At the time of the interview, MacGearailt was a contributor to Radio na Gaeltachta as a saoi, explaining the etymology of Irish phrases and words.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Micheál MacGearailt's home in Dingle, County Kerry, Ireland on August 13, 2015. This interview was conducted entirely in Irish and covers MacGearailt's family, his time in the United States (US), and his appreciation for the Irish language and culture. MacGearailt describes his family and their experiences immigrating to the US and returning to Ireland. He recounts his experiences living in Hartford, Connecticut and the connections he made there playing Gaelic football and speaking Irish with other members of the Gaelic Athletic Association. He discusses his work as an air traffic controller at Shannon Airport in County Clare, his work as a mail carrier in Hartford, and his decision to return to his family's farm in 1975.
  - Magee, Breandán, 2014; cuid34808 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_33)
    Breandán Magee was born in 1978 in Belfast, Northern Ireland. He received his master's degree at Duquesne University in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 2002. At the time of the 2014 interview, he was the Senior Director of Programs at Illinois Coalition for Immigrant and Refugee Rights.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll in Chicago, Illinois on November 22, 2014. The interview covers Breandán Magee's early life in Northern Ireland and his working life in the United States (US). Magee describes his parents and his childhood in Northern Ireland. He discusses his experiences of The Troubles in Belfast, Northern Ireland in 1980s, including his memories of bomb scares and his fear of his home being invaded as a child. He discusses his education and his decision to stay in the US after completing his master's degree at Duquesne University in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 2002. He discusses working at the Ireland Institute of Pittsburgh with the Walsh Visa Program and Wider Horizons Program in the early 2000s. He describes his work as the Executive Director at Chicago Irish Immigrant Support (CIIS), the senior programs started at CIIS under his direction, and his work at the time of the interview as the Senior Director of Programs at Illinois Coalition for Immigrant and Refugee Rights. He also discusses immigration policies in the US and their effect on all immigrants.
    Northern Ireland -- History -- 1968-1998 -- Personal narratives.
  - Maguire, Anne, Jan 24, 2009; cuid34621 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Anne Maguire (b. Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland, 1962), an activist for gay/lesbian rights, emigrated to New York in 1987. She was a founder of the Irish Lesbian and Gay Organization and the New York Lesbian Avengers. Her memoir, Rock the Sham! The Irish Lesbian & Gay Organization's Battle to March in New York City's St. Patrick's Day Parade, was published in 2006.
    Some of the key themes that Maguire focuses on are how her attitude to where 'home' (Ireland/New York) is has changed over time and how Irish American and Irish-born gays interacted.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview took place in New York City on January 24, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Mahon, Pat, Nov 14, 2007; cuid34622 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Pat Mahon discusses a range of topics from his Irish Catholic childhood in the Bronx to international Irish traditional music competitions and performance to life on Wall Street as an Irish Catholic New Yorker.
    He begins the interview discussing his family life and youth in the changing and diverse neighborhoods of the Bronx in the 1960s. As the oldest son of Irish immigrants, he and his three siblings were educated in Catholic grammar schools and he and his sister both tested into prestigious public high schools. He reflects on the importance of Irish identity for his parents and how they encouraged their children to build their own ethnic identity through music. Pat learned the button accordion and trained and competed with some well-known figures in the field of traditional music including Joannie Madden, Eileen Ivers, and Brian Conway. He describes his experience as the first American to win the All-Ireland championship in 1973 at the Fleadh in Listowel, Co. Kerry.
    It is clear from his discussion that music fills a central place in his life. He reflects on his short stint as a professional musician that interrupted his undergraduate education at Fordham University and how the reality of making a living sent him back to City University of New York-Lehman College for a degree in accounting. Despite a 20+ year career on Wall Street he has never abandoned his music and Mahon recalls how he pursued his passion for traditional music while stationed around the world for work, including years in Japan and England. His discussion of the traditional music world and its active participants is among the most fascinating highlights of the interview, in particular, his memories of performing with Eileen Ivers in Japan are wonderful.
    Mahon also discusses the various career paths of his siblings, particularly his two brothers, who pursued seemingly "typical" Irish vocations in law enforcement. He observes that the attacks on the World Trade Center altered the parameters of their work and made their occupations anything but typical. He speaks candidly about life on Wall Street and the ethnic culture of certain corporations and jobs in the financial services sector, but admitted that he did not suffer one way or the other by being Irish. As an ex-pat for most of his adult life and career, his identity as a "Yank" created more of an identity issue for him.
    He and his wife have three children who are themselves musicians but who identify themselves as European rather than Irish, American or Irish American. He reflects on how he and his wife met and the Irish background of his wife and her experience as an Irish dancer. He muses on the Riverdance craze and the boost it gave the Irish dance industry around the world, including the dance studio that his sister-in-law operates in Florida. In one anecdote he recalls how out of context it was to see young Japanese girls in "Sheila" wigs at competitions in Japan.
    This oral history with Pat Mahon was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 1 hour, 18 minutes, and 18 seconds long, on two CDs and has been logged at ten-minute intervals. The interview took place on November 14, 2007.
    Pat Mahon (b. Bronx, New York, 1958), a Bronx-born financial industry executive who lives in London. In 1973 he became the first American to win the All-Ireland button accordian championship. He continues to play music even as he travels the world for his career, including several years performing with an Irish band he formed while living in Tokyo.
  - Mahoney, Robert, 2015; cuid34809 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_81)
    Robert Mahoney was born in 1945 in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York.
    This interview was conducted by Marion Casey on January 14, 2015 at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House in Manhattan, New York. The interview contains Robert Mahoney's family history and early childhood. He describes the Greenwich Village neighborhood in which he grew up and his negative experiences in Catholic schools in the neighborhood. He retells how his father taught him to value his education and understand the dignity of labor by finding him labor intensive summer jobs.
  - Malone, Mary, Apr 7, 2011; cuid34623 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Mary Malone (b. New York, New York, 1939), the daughter of an immigrant from Ballymahon, County Longford, grew up in St. Nicholas of Tolentine parish in the Bronx. She worked for many years in Administration and Human Resources at AIG before retiring in 1996.
  - Malone, Stephen, 2014; cuid34810 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_6)
    Stephen Malone was born in 1969 in the Sunnyside neighborhood of Queens, New York. In 2014, he had been working as a carriage driver in New York for 27 years.
    This interview is conducted by Linda Dowling Almeida on June 2nd, 2014 at Clinton Stables in New York, New York. The interview covers Stephen Malone's family immigration story and his father's farrier business between 1967 and 1995. He recounts how he advocated against the exploitation of the carriage drivers by the City of New York with the help of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters. He shares the differences between his commercial carriage business and his father's carriage driving business.
  - Martin, Don, 2017; cuid34811 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_73)
    Don Martin was born in 1942 in the Morningside Heights neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He graduated from Columbia College in Manhattan with a degree in English Literature. He attended New York Law School in Manhattan, while working for the United States Trust Company. His worked for Post, Dumont and Crow in real estate law and the American Broadcasting Company as legal counsel.
    This interview was conducted by Linda Dowling Almeida on November 15, 2017 at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Don Martin's early life in the Morningside Heights neighborhood of Manhattan and his education at Mary Help of Christians in Manhattan. He recounts his memories of his work as legal counsel for the American Broadcasting Company and his political activism for the Irish Immigration Reform Movement.
  - McAllister, Brian, Nov 7, 2005; cuid34624 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Other Finding Aids
    The interview is approximately 1 hour and 40 minutes long. The interview took place on November 7, 2005, and the interviewers were Kerri Farrell, Linda Dowling Almeida, Marion R. Casey.
    Brian McAllister (b. 1932), president of McAllister Towing & Transport, a tugboat firm operating on the Eastern seaboard but principally in New York harbor.
  - McCann, Rosemary, Apr 5, 2012; cuid34625 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    Rosemary McCann (Ridgewood, New Jersey, 1955) has done a great deal of in-depth research on her family's immigration history. She has been able to trace her family back several generations to Cos. Armagh, Mayo, Meath, and Offaly.
  - McCarthy, Larry, Sep 4, 2013; cuid34626 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    Larry McCarthy (b. Co. Cork, Ireland, 1954) is a lifelong promoter of the Gaelic Athletic Association and a professor at Seton Hall University who received the Mayor's Award, New York City, for his work in support of Gaelic Park, New York.
  - McCarthy, Margaret, May 11, 2011; cuid34627 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Margaret McCarthy (b. White Plains, New York, 1953) is a photographer who has documented the peace and social justice movements of the last two decades through her photographs. She has published plays and poetry in literary magazines, journals and anthologies.
  - McCarthy, Monica, May 25, 2011; cuid34628 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Monica McCarthy (b. Castlebar, County Mayo, 1942), a second cousin of Irish Taoiseach Enda Kenny, was a civil servant in Dublin before emigrating to London in 1964 to work at the Irish Embassy there. She married an Irish American and the couple settled in Washington, D.C. Her grandparents had spent time in Philadelphia, where her mother was born in 1900.
  - McCarthy, Sr. Rita, Apr 8, 2009; cuid34629 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 40 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Tenalfy, New Jersey, on April 8, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Sr. Rita McCarthy (b. Lombardstown, Co. Cork, 1915), a Missionary Franciscan Sister, began her career in education at Our Lady of Peace, Brooklyn, in 1934. She retired as a school principal.
  - McDermott, Alice, Nov 12, 2010; cuid34630 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Alice McDermott (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1953), the Richard A. Macksy Professor of Humanities at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland, is a writer since 1983. She is the author of several books in which Irish America is central to understanding character including Charming Billy (1990) winner of the National Book Award for fiction.
  - McDermott, Hugh and McPhillips, John, Apr 8, 2012; cuid34631 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    Hugh McDermott and John McPhillips (b. Co. Tyrone, Northern Ireland, 1930) and (b. Montreal, Canada, 1929, d. 25 October 2012) both emigrated to Philadelphia in the 1950s, where they became involved with the Philadelphia Tyrone Society.
  - McDonagh, Orla, 2014; cuid34812 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_19)
    Orla McDonagh was born in 1972 in Dublin, Ireland. She studied piano at the Royal Irish Academy in Dublin. She moved to New York, New York in 1991 to study at the Juilliard School, receiving her bachelor's degree in piano performance in 1995, and received her Ph.D. in piano performance from Indiana University Bloomington in 1999. She was a professor of piano music theory at Indiana University between 1998 and 2001 and at Lewis & Clark College in Portland, Oregon between 2001 and 2010. In 2010 she returned to Ireland and taught at the Royal Irish Academy. At the time of the 2014 interview, McDonagh was teaching at the Royal Irish Academy, touring worldwide as a performer, and returning to Bloomington each summer to teach at Indiana University's Jacobs School of Music Piano Academy.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Orla McDonagh's home in Dublin, Ireland on July 31, 2014. The interview covers McDonagh's training as a pianist, her work as a music professor in the United States (US) and Ireland, and her experiences living in the US and Ireland. She discusses her parents and their siblings who emigrated from Ireland. She recounts her decision to study music at a young age and her education and training as a pianist. She discusses her education at the Juilliard School in New York and her experiences in New York in the 1990s. She describes her positions as a music professor at Indiana University Bloomington and Lewis & Clark College in Portland, Oregon, and her social and working lives in Bloomington and Portland. She discusses her position at the time of the interview as a professor at the Royal Irish Academy and summer instructor at Indiana University's Jacobs School of Music Piano Academy, and her feelings about both programs.
  - McFadden, Stephen, May 19, 2009; cuid34632 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 130 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on May 19, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Stephen McFadden (b. 1942), co-owner of Ryan McFadden's, a New York bar, is the son of emigrants from Co. Armagh and Co. Mayo immigrants.
  - McGimpsey, William, Jul 24, 2010; cuid34633 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - McGoldrick, Debbie, 2016; cuid34813 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_71)
    Debbie McGoldrick was born in 1965 in Mineola, New York. She graduated high school 1983 and graduated from Adelphi University in Garden City, New York in 1987. She worked at the Irish Echo between 1987 and 1991, before moving to the Irish Voice in 1991. She married Niall O'Dowd, founder of the Irish Voice, and has one daughter. At the time of the interview, McGoldrick was the editor of the Irish Voice.